George Henry Rickard Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
George Henry Rickard Papers
1885 - 1915
In 1885, George Henry Rickard was admitted to a workhouse in Middlesex, England and found to be of unsound mind. The collection is legal in nature and consists primarily of documents pertaining to Rickard’s estate, and for the most part, handled by his brother Richard Rickard through legal channels. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
1.84 linear feet (3 boxes)
Rickard, George Henry
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1969.0001
The George Henry Rickard Papers were purchased from the Old Hickory Bookshop in Brinklow, Maryland in April 1969 with funds donated by Mr. and Mrs. Charles Blatt.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
In 1885, George Henry Rickard was admitted to a workhouse in Middlesex, England and found to be of unsound mind. The medical officer of the workhouse, Dr. Joseph Rogers, wrote an affidavit providing evidence of insanity. Other statements regarding the patient and his estate were written by his brother Richard Rickard, his wife, Emily Proctor, and his sister, Mary Ann Alabaster. The collection reflects British attitudes around 1900 towards responsibility for the care of the mentally ill.
Rickard, George Henry; Workhouses; England
The collection is legal in nature and consists primarily of documents pertaining to Rickard’s estate, and for the most part, handled by his brother Richard Rickard through legal channels. A number of documents pertain to the upkeep of a house Rickard owned, as well as financial records of the Committee of his estate providing an accounting of his receipts, payments, and allowances from 1887-1915. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Brief. Evidence of insanity. Affidavit by Dr. Joseph Rogers, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Draft of affidavit of Richard Rickard, Undated (Box 1)
  - Copy draft. Certificate as to Committees, fortune and temporary maintenance, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Draft. Affidavit of Mrs. Mary Ann Alabaster proving the death of Richard Rickard the Elder, the next of kin, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Copy draft. Certificate as to fortune, income, and allowance for maintenance, 1887 (Box 1)
  - Certificate as to fortune, income, and allowance for maintenance, 1887 (Box 1)
  - Order appointing William Howard Winterbotham Committee of Person and Estate in place of Henry Leigh Pemberton, deceased, 1895 (Box 1)
  - Draft. Order as to lease of Freehold premises at Wandsworth, 1899 (Box 1)
  - Indenture (lease) between George Henry Rickard and Mary Ann Alabaster, 1899 (Box 1)
  - Draft. Affidavit of Mrs. Mary Ann Alabaster and another in support of application to Master of Lunacy for release of obligation under lease of June 15, 1899, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Draft of a charge. Interest in estate of Rickard to secure payment of costs, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Copy draft. Order for payment of dividends on the fund in court to Committee of Estate, 1893 (Box 1)
  - Copy draft. Order as to raising 200 pounds for repairs to No. 1 Haldon Road, 1910 (Box 1)
  - Order as to raising 200 pounds for repairs of No. 1 Haldon Road, 1910 (Box 2)
  - Repairs made to No. 1 Haldon Road, Undated (Box 2)
  - Summons to sell freehold premises at Wandsworth, 1899 (Box 2)
  - Summons for directions as to lease of No. 1 Haldon Road, 1906 (Box 2)
  - Affidavits of Arthur Theodore Williams, 1899 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit re lease of No. 1 Haldon Road, 1899 (Box 2)
  - Affidavit of Arthur Theodore Williams, 1910 (Box 2)
  - Exhibits, 1910 (Box 2)
  - Report of Messrs. Humbert and Flint, 1898 (Box 2)
  - Summons for leave to expend 200 pounds on repairs to No. 1 Haldon Road, 1910 (Box 2)
  - Committee of Rickard’s estate. First account of his receipts, payments, and allowances from 1887-1888 (Box 2)
  - Committee of Rickard’s estate. Second and final account of his receipts, payments, and allowances from 1889-1892 (Box 2)
  - Committee of Rickard's estate. First account of his receipts, payments, and allowances from 1895-1897 (Box 2)
  - Committee of Rickard’s estate. Second account of receipts, payments, and allowances from 1897-1900 (Box 2)
  - Committee of Rickard’s estate. Third account of his receipts, payments, and allowances from 1900-1903 (Box 2)
  - Committee of Rickard’s estate. Fourth account of his receipts, payments, and allowances from 1903-1906 (Box 2)
  - Committee of Rickard’s estate. Fifth account of his receipts, payments, and allowances from 1906-1909 (Box 2)
  - Committee of Rickard’s estate. Sixth account of his receipts, payments, and allowances from 1909-1912 (Box 2)
  - Committee of Rickard’s estate. Seventh account of his receipts, payments, and allowances from 1912-1915 (Box 2)